It was a small town by a small river and a small lake.
In a small northern part
of a Midwest state.
There wasn't so much
wilderness around
that you couldn't
see the town.
On the other hand, there wasn't
so much town around
that you couldn't see and feel
and touch the wilderness.
And the town was full
of fences to walk on
and sidewalks to skate on.
And the muted cries
and laughter of boys and girls.
Full of costumes, dreams
and pumpkin spirits
preparing for the greatest
night of the year.
Better than Easter,
better than Christmas.
Halloween.
'Jenny,
you're gonna raise the dead'
'with all that racket
down there.'
'Just lookingfor another broom, mom.'
'You can alwaysuse the new vacuum cleaner.'
Ha ha, very funny.
Pip is really
gonna love this.
'A little more on my own.
There.That's it.'
'Oh, yeah,
by the way, dad..'
'Sorry about using
up all your gauze.'
It's okay, Ralph.
I-I just hope no one needs
any first aid, tonight.
Or you have to go to the
bathroom anytime soon.
Gotta go, can't keep
Pip waiting.
Yeah.Bet it'll even scare Pip.
'Tom Skeleton,
you're one lucky boy.'
A name like Skelton
on this kinda night.
Oh-oh. Oh, Pip's gonna
kill me for being late.
Woo!
'Trick-or-treat.'
Trick-or-treat.
- Yeah.
- Ha ha ha.
- Alright, we made it.
- It's gonna be great.
I'm ready for the treats.
But I get more candy
than you do, Wally.
- You and who else?
- Take that back.
- Come on, Wally.
- Hey, you guys, stop it.
Wait, where's Pip?
He's never been late
for a Halloween
in a million zillion years.
- Bet its some kinda trick.
- Sure it is.
For once, let's surprise him.
Come on.
Pip!
Ah, yes, Joe Pipkin.
Some say, that on
the day he was born
all the soda pop bottles
in the world fizzed over.
Pipkin, who could
yell louder, sing better
and eat more popcorn.
Pip, the greatest boy
who ever lived.
There's his house.
- Huh?
- Impossible.
It can't be.
What?
'Where are the jack-o-lanterns?'
And the corn shocks
on the porch.
'And monsters clinging to the roof.'
Something's wrong,
awfully wrong.
Oh, Pip.
Hey, Tom, look at that.
'Oh, my gosh, it's a note.'
'What's it say?'
"Dear Tom, and all the gang,
didn't mean to spoil
"your Halloween.
Off to the hospital.
Something about appendicitis,
don't worry."
'Signed, Pip.'
Appendicitis?
You can die
from that, right?
"P.S.
Go ahead without me,
I'll catch up. Ready, set, go."
But we can't start
Halloween without Pip.
It wouldn't be official.
There's a shortcut
to the hospital.
No, tha-that shortcut.
Come on, you all heard him.
Ready, set, go!
Think Pip's gonna
be surprised, Tom?
He did say to start
Halloween without him.
It'll be worth it
to see the look on his face.
Woodside, comin' through.
Jenny, wait. Stop. Wait up.
Oh!
There. There's the shortcut.
'Not the ravine.'
Eh, got any other shortcuts
to choose from, Tom?
Ralph does have
a point there.
I think.
What did I tell you? Look.
'It's Pip. Pip!'
Hey, I-I can see
right through him.
Nah, it's just this
funny moonlight.
The important thing is,
he isn't sick.
But what about the hospital?
Don't you get it?
It was a joke all the time.
The ambulance,
that note on the door.
What a trickster. Hey, Pip.
You sure had us fooled!
Where's your Halloween costume?
'Hey, Pip, wait up.'
Not you too, Tom.
Come on, Wally.
The ravine.
The ravine was filled
with varieties of darkness.
Night, shadows, toad eyes
and raven beaks.
The ravine, the birth place
of wild mushrooms.
Pale toadstool, whispers
and ripping's which call
"Come, stay, linger and hide.
"Hide here forever. Never go.
Stay, stay."
Huh?
Woo! Now, you know, I never
believe in haunted houses.
'But that sure look likes
one haunted house to me.'
Ah, yes.
The house looked like it had
been cut of black marble.
With many chimneys, the roof
seemed a vast cemetery.
Each flue signifying
the burial place
of some old forgotten
God of fire.
'This is the best prank he's ever played.'
But it's not fair. He's gonna
trick-or-treat ahead of us.
Yeah, Pip always
gets the most candy.
But that house is haunted.
Darn right, otherwise
why would Pip lead us to it.
Oh, yeah.
'Oh, my gosh.'
This is no time
to hold back, Tom. Remember?
Ready, set, go!
'Why, it's a Marley knocker.'
You know, a Christmas carol,
Scrooge and Marley.
So, who's gonna knock?
You!
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay then, I'll do it.
Oh, great, now you've
done it, Jenny.
'Enter.'
Oh, my gosh.
Tom!
- Ah.
- Ooh.
Why have you disrupted me?
And my business?
- I..
Please, sir. Trick?
Or treat?
Oh, I really have
no time for this.
'But sir,
it's Halloween and--'
So, you've tricked me?
Is that it?
What woulda treat
be then, eh? Hm?
Well, uh, we saw our
friend coming here.
If you let him out,
that'd be a treat.
'Yeah.'
Who are you?
I'm... name's Tom Skeleton.
Know why are your
wearing bones, boy?
Bah, didn't think so.
- And you?
- My friends call me--
Why so dressed upin
an ancient mummies rags? Hm?
Time's up.
And you... the big one.
M-me sir?
Why a monster's face? Hm?
- And what about you, girl?
- Jenny.
Why are you wearing
a costume of a witch? Hm?
No thoughts, eh?
Oh, I'm wasting my breathe.
All dressed up
for All Hallows' Eve.
But you don't know why,
or what or even from where.
- Pity.
- And you, sir?
Eh, who are you?
Oh, yes, of course, hm,
I beg your pardon.
Moundshroud is the name.
'Carapace Clavicle Moundshroud.'
'Is that not
a fine name, children?'
Does it... ring?
But I have work to do, tonight.
No treats... only trick.
So, if you'll excuse me.
'I'm onquite
a tight schedule.'
Huh!
Pip!
- You-you're a ghost.
- 'So, there you are.'
Stop! We still have
our appointment, you and I.
Now, see what you've done.
- 'Pip.'
- 'Pipkin.'
'Woo,
there must be a million of 'em.'
'Pumpkins!'
Look at 'em all.
A pumpkin tree.
'No, a Halloween tree.'
The pumpkins on the tree were not mere pumpkins.
Each had a face sliced in it.
Each face was different.
Every nose was a weirder nose.
Every mouth smiled hideously
in some new way.
A thousand grimaces
and twice times
the thousand glares
of fresh cut eyes.
Each blink held
the remnant holiday spirit
of years gone by.
Pipkin, where are you going?
- We're over here.
- Why is he goin' up the tree?
Uh.
'Don't bother.
Now, stay up there.'
Argh.
No, Pip, it's too high.
Come down from there.
What are you..
'Huh! Look!'
'That pumpkin!'
'It looks just like, Pip.'
Argh!
Come on, we gotta help him.
Children, no.
No more interference.
Hold on, Pip, don't move.
You've had your fun, boy.
Don't touch that.
'Got you.'
It belongs to me.
Bring it here.
Inexcusable.
Inexcusable behavior!
- Pip, Pip.
- Over here, Pip.
- Hey, Pipkin.
- Oh, my gosh.
Pip!
- He's melting.
- Where'd he go?
'Help me!'
No!
Bother, bother,
bother, I say.
'Do you've any idea
what you've done?'
Now, my entire night's
schedule is thrown off.
What'd you do with Pip?
Where did you send him?
Oh, I didn't send him
anywhere, skeleton.
- Where is he?
- Yeah.
Oh, he must not have
liked my company.
So, he escaped.
Escaped, I might add, with
a pumpkin that is my property.
Well then, Cara-Clava..
Clavicle.
But you may call me,
Mr. Moundshroud.
Whatever your name is,
you bring him back right now.
'If only life were that easy.
Hm.'
By now, Pip's escaped
to the undiscovered country.
No telling how long it will
take me to find him again.
Find him?
Can we go with you?
We can help.
Impossible. You've helped quite
enough already. Thank you.
But anything's possible
on Halloween, right?
Ha! What do you know
about Halloween?
'Four meddlers come
barging into my house.'
'Blundering into my business.'
Not even knowing why.
You are dressed as a skeleton,
witch, mummy or..
Hm, wait a minute.
It is a long trip.
And it's hours before dawn.
So, I've... we should
have enough time.
If we fly fast enough.
Yes.
And far enough.
Yes, yes.
We might be able
to catch Pipkin.
Grab his pumpkin fire soul and
have a scavenger huntas well.
'So you can find out who you
are. What you are made off.'
And retrieve your Pipkin
at the same time.
Well, will you come with me?
And solve three
mysteries in one?
Yes!
What fun then.
The undiscovered country it is.
Feast your eyes,
a thousand Halloweens
wait out there
to swallow us whole.
That barn, and on
the sides of the barn
'the makingsof an
October Kite. You see?'
This way, skeleton.
This road, mummy.
'This fence, witch.
This meadow, monster.'
Do you see?
And they did see.
They saw the poster paper
tapestry of circus beasts.
Pasted on the barn side
years ago.
It was as if
the captured animals
were waiting to be released.
- Oh.
- Oh, my gosh.
Oh, my gosh.
Let's build
the kite then, shall we?
Time for you to help.
- Huh.
- Uh.
They seized huge rows of animals
from the weathered walls.
They tore off
patches of fangs.
Scripts of piercing eyes
and sheets of claws and tails.
The unshackled beasts cried.
And assembled in freed
leaps and bounds.
Oh, my gosh!
- Will it fly us?
- I thought you'd never ask!
'It won't fly straight.'
A tail. We need a tail.
Right, boy.
Who else for the tail?
- I'm next.
- Not before me.
- Ah.
Fly.
'Fly.'
Ah, I just remembered
I hate heights.
Two times two is four.
Four times four is sixteen.
Sixteen times sixteen is..
256 is 65500..
It's Pip.
Pip.
Seven hundred and forty.
'Pipkin.'
Where's he going?
Not where? When?
Four thousand, Halloweens ago.
Pipkin with my pumpkin
has gone ahead.
Or should I say, passed.
The moon began to blink,
faster and faster
it began to wax to wane.
Until a 1000 times over
it flickered.
And then flickering changed
the landscape below.
'Egypt.'
'But it's brand new.'
'That means we really have
gotten back in time.'
Four thousand years.
Hey.
O-oh, o-oh.
Ar-are those
real life ghosts?
They prefer being
called spirits.
- Tryin' to get into the houses?
- True.
And the food on the porches
is for them?
'Seems so.'
Why, it's good old-fashioned
trick-or-treat.
- Four thousand years ago?
- Yes, imagine that.
Ah, look there.
'That ghost, uh, spirit.'
Sure, let's sneak up on him.
'Pip.'
'Hold on wait.'
'Here we are.'
Enter. Sit. You're welcome.
- Ah.
- Okay.
Ew!
- Ah!
- Uh.
Oh, my gosh.
'Who's that?'
Our great-grandfather.
Don't make a fuss.
'He doesn't look very good.'
Oh, he's been dead
for 67 years.
So, what's he doing here?
Once a year, at the feast
of the ghosts
we invite him out
to sit with us.
Eat.
Don't you wish we had
a custom like this back home?
Dinner for the dead.
Ow!
Oh.
What?
Help!
Well, children. Seems we won't
have time for dessert.
Come on, Mr. Moundshroud,
he's getting too far ahead.
Huh!
The time is come. Hurry.
Race, run.
Your three mysteries await.
- Wow. Just look at these.
- They're giants.
Pip, didn't go in there, did he?
Yes.
- Oh, great.
- Go ahead, Tom.
- No, Ralph should go first.
- It's all yours, Wally.
No, you first. I insist.
Betcha, Pip sent this
out here to show us the way.
It's got me.
'Hold on.'
'We're coming after you.'
Wait up.
You, with the mummy wrappings
and mummy face.
Who? Me?
Day is killed by night.
Summer by winter.
'Osiris the sun God destroyed
by his brother, darkness.'
The seasons.
Is tha-that what the Egyptians
thought of Halloween?
- You tell me.
- Ah.
Why do you wear that costume?
'Oh, you're a mummy, boy.'
'Because that's how Egyptians'
'dressed up their dead
for eternity.'
Spun around
in a cocoon of threads.
They hoped to come forth
like fresh butterflies
in some far dear-loving
underworld.
Know your cocoon, boy.
Touch the strange stuffs.
Then, then every day
was Halloween day then.
Yes, every day, Ralph.
Very good.
But, but what about Pipkin?
It may be too late.
They are wrapping him up
as a gift to eternity, now!
You don't mean like,
right now?
Save them, Ralph.
I'm coming, Pip.
'Ralph.'
Pipkin?
'Ralphy, is that you?'
Yeah, yeah it's me.
I'm gonna get you out of here.
'I'm fading.'
No, you can't leave now.
What about all our plans?
You said someday you'd teach me
how to bat left-handed.
And you're the only friend
who's never made fun
of my wearing glasses.
'Learning to bat left-handed
isn't so hard, Ralphy.'
Oh, great. Now what do I do?
Come along, Pipkin.
You've had your fun.
You and I have an appointment
to keep. You must keep it.
No!
Ah!
The air vents. Come on.
Yes. Find him. Catch him.
Wait up, Ralph.
Hurry, but don't fall.
- Oh, my gosh.
- Wally, don't jinx it, okay?
Oh.
'Pip!'
Hurry back.
Four corners, kids. Grab on.
He can hide, but if we hurry,
we can go seek.
Oh!
Oh, my gosh, look down there.
Wally, don't you dare tell
me how high we are.
Time to celebrate, children.
'Happy New Year.'
'No, it's Halloween.'
'Well,
maybe in our time it's All Hallows' Eve.'
'But in this time,
it's New Year's Eve.'
'The true end of summer,
and cold start of winter.'
'Happy New Year.'
Down in the crowd.
Is that him below?
No, he's there above.
What is this place?
Where are we?
When are we?
It's old time, children.
Ancient times. Stonehenge.
You need courage tonight.
It's the Dark Ages,
and this is the longest
darkest night in all dark time.
- Oh, my gosh.
- What? What?
Is that you, Pip?
'In these dark times,
people thought'
'that on this special night'
'those who had died during the
year were turned into beasts.'
'Became animals.'
Dogs, wild boars
or worst of all... cats.'
'Black as bad luck.
Black as sin.'
Pip?
'Black as night.'
Easy, pip.
Steady, boy.
We-we, we'll save you.
No, I'll get him.
Come here, Pip.
Pip. No, come back.
Tom, I-I think
this is the last year
ever go trick-or-treat
with you guys. Okay?
Peek-a-boo.
There was a hustle of brooms in the broom works.
An immense traffic jams
of brooms for witches
to perch upon.
It was as if all earth's
forests gave up their branches
in one broom and fling.
And scouring autumn fields
cut clean and throttled tight
such cereal grains
as made good sweepers,
thrashers, and beaters.
Hey, you know what that is?
A Broom Festival.
And they're making brooms.
But not ordinary brooms.
Touch them.
Feel them.
Broomsticks for witches.
For you.
Me?
Whoops!
Ah.
Ride him, Jenny.
Anyone else care to try it?
- Whoa.
Oh, my gosh. Oh, my gosh.
Oh, my gosh.
Jenny, listen to me.
No, I wanna be
back on the ground.
Just put me back
on the ground.
'Where's your spirit of adventure?'
Witches have nothing
to fear from their brooms.
Betcha, it's no different
from riding your bike.
My bike, like my bike.
Hey, you're right.
Now, how about
follow the leader?
Look.
I can't believe it.
While flying, I saw, I saw..
Pip. Was it Pip?
No. Witches. Everywhere.
Of course. It can't
be Halloween without witches.
- Then they really were witches?
- Well, yes and no.
- Could they fly broomsticks?
- Not really.
- They could talk to the dead?
- Nope.
Make hairy warts grow on people?
Sorry, no.
Make people jump
by sticking pins in dolls?
Not to my knowledge.
Well, heck then,
what could they do?
Nothing.
Nothing?
'Ah,
plenty claimed they could.'
But that was just a means
to protect their privacy.
Ever wondered what
the word witch really means?
Well, no. Not until tonight.
Ha ha ha.
Wished that information.
In the Dark Ages anyone with
half a brain, any knowledge
had his wits about him. Yes.
So, anyone too smart
was called..
A witch.
Exactly.
And the really smart ones,
ones with the wits called it
Magic. Magic.
In every town,
in every tiny village
the old religions hid out.
And all the
little lollygagging cults
all flavors and types
scrambled to survive.
By every crossroad
and by every haystack
dark forms jumped
across flames
as fires burned everywhere.
'In the end all Europe was a cloud of witches' smoke.'
Anyone want to be a witch?
No, no, not me.
'Pip!'
Wonderful, let's play tag.
Now, Pip, the pumpkin doesn't
belong to you anymore.
Hold on, Pip.
Grab on.
Hurray. Let's show 'em, Jenny.
Some switch, huh, Jenny?
You saving me, huh?
Don't fall, Pip.
What if I need you to talk me
down out of an apple tree again?
Tighter, Pip.
If I ever lost you..
Hey, no tears. Wouldn't you just
hate to have Tom see you cry?
- Yeah. Fun and games are over.
- No, they're not.
Follow me if you can.
Ready, set, go.
There's got to be two zillion,
ten billion acres of air
wrapped round the world.
Which half-acre
is he headed for?
- Now, what?
- I'm still a witch, right?
I got the wits, follow me.
You heard her. Let's go.
There. There he is.
Well, is he here?
Gotta be. I can feel him
in my bones.
Where is he, Mr. Moundshroud?
Where, you may ask. Hm.
Why, hiding out.
Protecting his pumpkin soul.
How observant of you, skeleton.
But to be precise,
it is my pumpkin.
Come out, come out,
wherever you are.
I have a riddle
for you, monster.
- Can't you ask someone else?
- No, no, it's your turn now.
What's bigger and stronger
than demons and witches?
A place so big, it holds back
the night and nightmares?
What's bigger
than devils and ghosts?
Bigger?
Ah..
- A cathedrals?
- Well done, monster.
Yes. Places where a running
and renegade child
can hide and take sanctuary.
Sanctuary. Sanctuary. Sanctuary.
'Sanctuary.'
- 'Help.'
- Pip.
Ralph, Wally, Jenny.
I think we're getting warmer.
Something wrong,
Mr. Moundshroud?
Yeah, you fool
half the night to catch Pip.
So how come you're not
going up to get him?
Well, simply because,
there are some places
where I'm not
as welcome as others.
Ah, why don't you
collect Pip for me?
Please. Wally.
But how do we reach him?
There are ways. After all,
tonight of all nights is still..
- Halloween.
- Precisely.
So why not finish building
the cathedral, with your feet?
Are you kidding?
No, call the stones
with your feet.
You coming, Mr. Moundshroud?
Ha ha ha, you know
I'm always with you.
Carry on.
Come on, guys.
Pip is counting on us.
Leap? Run. They will follow.
Oh!
Step lightly.
- Sorry, Wally.
- Ah.
- Oh!
- Bravo.
They ran on pure,
windy light, only to have bricks, and stones
and mortar shuffle like cards,
deal themselves solid
and take form beneath
their toes and heels.
Oh, enough.
There, much better, much better.
Notre Dame,
I think we've built Notre Dame.
- But this can't be Notre Dame.
- Why not?
Can't you see what's missing?
- Monster faces.
- You know, stone devils.
Marble demons.
'Gargoyles.'
Ever wonder why
we like dressing up
as monsters, beasts,
and ornery critters?
Monsters remind us
of all the dark nights
'and all fears and nightmares.'
Go ahead, monster. They're
waiting for your summons.
The unemployed of all midnight Europe
shivered in their stone sleep.
And came awake.
All the old beasts,
all the old tales
and unused demons put by,
reared at the whistle
and in spectral dust devils
of propulsion, arrived.
'Monster,
there's your carved stone quarry.'
Gargoyles, now the building
is finished, Tom.
'Tom, Jenny, Ralph, Wally,
are you here?'
Where are you, Pip?
'Here.'
Oh, my gosh!
'Ge-get me, get me out of here.'
- I'm scared.
- It's Gargoyle language?
He can talk when the rain
comes out of his mouth.
Or the wind blows
over his teeth.
Come on,
just a little bit higher.
You can do it.
No cutting in line, plenty
for all. One at a time.
Hold it. I'm the only
live Gargoyle here.
- Right, Mr. Moundshroud?
- Indeed.
So, it's up to me.
Tom, right.
Rob, left.
Together now.
Whoa!
Oh, Pipkin,
what's happened to you?
- I think I'm dying.
- You are not!
You tried, Wally.
All of you did.
Shut up! Shut up, will you?
Don't quit, keep running,
escape, we'll follow.
- Gotta go now, Wally.
- No, no, Pip, you can't!
Wait, will you?
Remember that time,
those fireworks
I stored in my bedroom.
The one's who started the fire.
Uh, sure smoked up your house.
An-and you took
the blame for me.
I never thanked you for that.
Oh!
Wally. Come on, two points.
Toss it right up here.
- Goodbye, Wally.
- No, Pip, I won't let you go.
No!
Ah!
'That's it. Get the pumpkin.'
Oh.
No.
I'm coming, Pip!
Come on, we can't loose him now.
There's no escape.
I'll chalk his course
to a final graveyard.
'Well, we've arrived children.'
'Our final destination.'
But where are we?
Listen, guitars!
And those must
be skeleton bones.
No, marimbas
and xylophones.
Castanets.
'Hooray!'
That sounds like a bon fire.
'Mexico!'
'Look, all the graveyards!'
'Where are all those
people going?'
El Dia de los Muertos.
The Day of the Dead.
Back home, we'd never think
going to a graveyard
on Halloween.
But this looks like fun!
Yeah! Alright!
'Look at little funerals for sale!'
Are those real coffins?
- Hey! Look!
- What's this?
Whoa! The newspapers
are full of bones!
Mexican Halloween's
are sure better that ours.
Huh! Pipkin! He must be
around here some place.
Oh... Ah!
Oh!
O-oh!
Sweet skulls!
- Crystal sugar candy skulls!
- Oh! What's going on?
'Sweet skulls!
Sweet skulls. Crystal sugar candy skulls.'
'Hey, look at the candy heads.'
Tell me your name,
I give you your skull.
Tom!
How about Ralph?
Ha ha.
- Um, um, Wally!
- Ha ha ha, Jenny!
Oh!
Ha ha ha.
Hold them in your palms.
Bite it, swallow it
and survive.
Come out the far black
tunnel of Halloween
and be glad, oh, so glad
you are alive! Ha ha ha.
Hey, we better look for Pip now,
it's getting late.
Yes! For All Hallows' Eve
it to be away. Head's up!
Hey! What's goin' on?
Whoa! Whoa!
- Ooh.
- Ah.
- That was fun.
- What's next?
No more time
for games, children.
The night ends here.
Dow-down in that hole?
Down in the catacombs,
he's waiting.
Simon says, "Bring him up."
And be extra careful
with my pumpkin.
We'll bring him up but we'll
keep him for ourselves.
Bravery spoken.
Pip would have liked that.
Hurry the dawn is approaching.
'Mummy's.'
Their families couldn't pay
the rent on their graves.
So the grave digger
put them down here.
A little too dry for me.
Shh.
What're you doing there, Pip?
I have to stay.
I'm trapped.
But if you stay there
you'll stay forever.
Tourist will buy tickets
to come look at you.
Pip, come on out it's just us.
Huh.
'Oh, my gosh.'
They're alive.
- What do we do?
- I don't know.
Tell me, why do you
wear bones skeleton?
Because of my name.
Oh, have you learnt
nothing tonight, boy.
Because maybe if we face
death eye ball to eye ball
it loses its power
over us, it can't scare us.
Excellent, Tom.
So I've got to save, Pip. Alone.
Ah.
'You can do it.'
'Don't look back!
Don't look back!'
'Just go straight!'
Woo! Woo! Woo!
Oh, Pip, don't die.
I'm sorry. So sorry.
What do you mean, Tom?
You came through.
No, all this tonight
is my fault.
I once wished for something
to happen to you
so I could be leader
for a change.
But I never thought something
like appendicitis.
Ah, don't be silly, Tom.
I'll let you lead anytime.
Huh? What's happening?
Pip! No!
Ha ha ha! This truly
has been fun, hasn't it?
And I know just where
I'm going to hang this.
No! I got
to him first. I won.
Sorry, this never was a contest.
It's rent was past due,
it's simple and plain.
- That's not fair.
- You cheated!
You said if we came with you
and solve the mysteries
of Halloween,
we could save Pipkin.
Children, it's business.
With his illness,
his rent came due
and there was no payment.
He's mine now!
- Well, we tried.
- We did our best.
Let's go home.
No! Wait!
Mr. Moundshroud,
I'll make his payment for him.
You? What could you possibly
have to pay with?
Money?
Currency?
Coin of the realm?
What if uh..
'What if what, boy?'
Well, what if I gave you, uh,
something of value.
Say, A year of my life.
Oh!
You'd do that for him?
Yes. A year from
the end of my life.
It's yours if it would save Pip.
One precious year from the
far burned out candle end
of your life, eh?
Think before you answer!
You won't miss it now,
but 60 years from today
to 72 or 80 when I come
for payment, you may regret it.
Is he worth it,
this friend of yours, hm?
More than you'll ever know.
Hm. One boy's love.
'Take one of mine too.'
- And mine.
- I'm in.
Four for one makes
good business, doesn't it?
Yes! I like it!
Here then!
Chew, swallow,
swallow and chew.
- Pip!
- Wait!
Come back!
Where's he going?
After all this,
only one place.
Home!
But we saved him, didn't we?
Will he live, Mr. Moundshroud?
Come! Our night journey is over!
One last game
of musical chairs!
Moundshroud sprung about like a whirlwind.
His arms flung out,
cut the air in slicing
grabs and swoops
that shook the mummies
in earthquakes of bones.
Fall down,
whistled the whirlwind.
Fall up, was the echo.
They tumbled through the sky
like a self made storm.
It was the end of their
4000 year flight.
From Egyptian crypts.
To English broom fields.
To French quarry works.
To Mexican bone yards.
They swooped homeward.
Once around the court house.
And twice around the pumpkin
burning tree.
And a final time
around old Moundshroud's house.
Where dust sifted out windows
to greet them.
And that children
is Halloween!
All rolled up in one.
Night and day.
Summer and winter.
Life and death.
Four thousand years ago,
100 years or this year.
'One place or another.'
'The celebrations
are all the same.'
El Dia de los Muertos.
Day of the Dead.
Feast of ghosts.
All Hallows' Eve.
Halloween!
I thank you for a most
amusing and profitable evening.
And after what you've done
for your friend.
One I will never forget.
- But what about--
- Run!
See for yourselves!
The last grand trick-or-treat!
'Look! It's his pumpkin.'
'Oh, my gosh! He must be okay.'
Hi, guys.
- Pipkin!
- You are alive!
Hooray!
They took my appendix out.
For a while,
I thought I was a goner.
Imagine that.
Anyway, thanks for... everything.
Huh? What are you talking about?
We didn't do anything.
- Nothing.
- Heck.
Gosh.
Is that so?
Well, I had dreams
about Pyramids, Stonehenge
Paris and Mexico.
Like I said, thanks.
Then a great, wondrous, happy,
tiredness gathered
in their eyelids
and arms and feet.
The witch and mummy
and monster and skeleton
ran back to their own houses
to remember this special night
that they would never in all
their lives, ever forget.
Old Moundshroud blew out
one last candle.
Causing it to
flicker and flare.
The wind blew in and out
the fresh cut mouth
with the whispered song.
A 1000 pumpkins were seized
and blown into the sky.
That is all but one pumpkin.
Pip's pumpkin.
Pip's spirit and soul.
That was traded for and saved
on that Halloween night
So long ago.